<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iethroes counsell to Moses: or, A direction for magistrates A sermon preached at St. Saviours in Southwarke. March 5. 1621. before the honourable iudges by that reverent divine Thomas Sutton Dr. in Divinity.</title>
            <author>Sutton, Thomas, 1585-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2085:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iethroes counsell to Moses: or, A direction for magistrates A sermon preached at St. Saviours in Southwarke. March 5. 1621. before the honourable iudges by that reverent divine Thomas Sutton Dr. in Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Sutton, Thomas, 1585-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A direction for magistrates.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173660:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IETHROES COVNSELL TO MOSES: OR, A DIRECTION FOR MAGISTRATES. A Sermon preached at S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Saviours in Southwarke. March 5. 1621. Before the Honourable Iudges by that Reverent Divine THOMAS SVTTON D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> in Divinity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LEVIT. 19.15.</bibl>
               <p>Ye ſhall doe no unrighteouſneſſe in judgement; thou ſhalt not respect the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty; but in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES, dwelling in <hi>Red-croſſe-ſtreete.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173660:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173660:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR ROBERT DVCE, Knight Barronet, Lord Major of the City of LONDON: and to the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the Sheriffes and Aldermen of the ſame; <hi>W. I.</hi> P. wiſheth increaſe of knowledge and grace in Chriſt here, that you may reigne with him hereafter in glory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING a Sermon come to my hands, of the Counſell of <hi>Iethro</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of the Lord, how hee might with more eaſe to himſelfe and the people decide all controverſies; as it was preached before the Iudges in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> by that Reverend and learned Divine, <hi>Mr. Dr. Sutton,</hi> late Preacher at <hi>Saviours:</hi> The which Sermon giveth direction, not onely to Iudges, but alſo to all Magiſtrates in the Land, how to carry themſelves in their ſeverall places against all offenders, and betwixt man and man: It being a ſubject of ſo neceſſary a uſe; it is thought meete to publiſh it in theſe evill times, becauſe the ſeate of Iustice is now had in much contempt by many who live as if there were no God in heaven to behold their wickedneſſe, nor
<pb facs="tcp:173660:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Magiſtrate on earth to puniſh their horrible crimes. And ſeeking out for a Patron, I thought fit to dedicate it to your Honour, and Worſhips: To your Honour, who in your Shreivalty ſhewed your great zeale and love to the Goſpell of Chriſt, that upon a diſcovery of the practiſes of Ieſuites and Priests, roſe at midnight to execute the warrant of <hi>Sir Robert Nanton,</hi> then Secretary to King <hi>Iames</hi> of moſt bleſſed memory; where was taken ſeventeene Altars for their Popiſh Maſſe, ten Copes, twelve or thirteene Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, above ten thouſand Popiſh bookes, beſides ſeverall pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of Letters, partly come from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and going to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> &amp;c. And ſeeing the Lord hath advanced your Honour into the chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> under our gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King <hi>CHARLES,</hi> the Lord give you courage and zeale, against all Popiſh ſuperstitition and Idolatry: requeſting you that you would be pleaſed to peruſe the ſhort directions in it: That ſo you may with the reſt of your Right Worſhipfull Brethren, the better direct all and ſeverall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in their ſeverall places, under you in your ſeverall Wards; that they alſo may be men of courage, fearing God. To that end I beſeech the Lord of heaven, who directed his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo to direct your hearts, that you may have both the courage and zeale of <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt all idolatrous Priests and Ieſuites that ſwarme in the Land, whoſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous practiſes this worthy Sermon doth at large diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and ſo put them out of all hope of gaining any Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites here among you. Thus daily praying unto the Lord on your behalfe, I humbly take my leave.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, and Worſhips, to be commanded in the Lord Ieſus: <hi>W. I.</hi> P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:173660:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Dr. SVTTONS Prayer.</head>
            <p>OH moſt gracious and moſt glorious God, before whom the Sunne and the Moone become as darkneſſe, the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſtand amaſed, and the glorious Cherubims are glad that they may cover and hide their faces, as not daring to behold that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible greatneſſe, and that infinite goodneſſe which thou art; with what confidence ſhall we forlorne ſinners be ever once able to appeare before thy all ſeeing providence, that terrible and angry countenance, that ſinne-revenging juſtice of thine, which is ſo fierce and terrible, that it will ſhake the heavens, melt the mountaines, dry up the ſeas, and make the talleſt Cedars in Lebanon to tremble: Good Lord, where ſhall we hide our ſelves from thy preſence; maſſes of corruption, mountaines of ſinne, dead and dry trees, fit fewell for thy fierce wrath to worke upon: if we ſhould climbe up into heaven to hide us from thee, thou art there, or goe downe into the bottome and depth of hell, thou art there alſo; or take the wings of the morne, and fly to the utmoſt part of the ſeas even there alſo will thy allſeing eye behold us, and thy right hand will quickly viſit and finde us out: we will therefore here diſſolve and melt our ſelves into a floud and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of many teares, bewailing and bemoaning our wofull and miſerable eſtate; for albeit by reaſon of that ſoule Chaos, and ſtaine of naturall corruption and originall ſinne, we have deſerved long ſince to have had the ſweete iſſue of all thy good bleſſings to be ſtopped and dried up, thy milde and gentle corrections to be turned into the ſodaine execution of bloody tortures and fearefull judgements upon us even in this life, and at our departing out of this world to be plunged everlaſtingly into a pit of deſtruction, there to be fryed and ſcorched with Satan and his Angels for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. And yet for all this, O Lord, wee have never ceaſed to adde oyle unto this flame, and to blow up the coales of thy feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpleaſure, through the hot and eager purſuit of many loud crying actuall ſinnes and tranſgreſſions; ſo that from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foote, there is not one place ſound
<pb facs="tcp:173660:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> or whole within us, but we are all full of ſores and ſwellings, and botches, full of ſinne, full of corruption: our underſtandings which ſhould have knowne thee to be our true God, and him whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt our Redeemer, theſe are blinded and miſſed with ignorance and doubting, our affections which ſhould have beene good guides to have directed our feete into the way of peace, they are become ſwift meſſengers of Satan to buffet us; our bodies which ſhould have beene ſweet Temples for thy bleſſed Spirit to dwell and lodge in, they are ſinks of ſinne, and cages of filthy birds: our eyes O God, are like open win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and doores to receive ſinne, our hearts like common Innes to lodge ſinne, our heads like skilfull Politicians to contrive ſinne, our tongues ſmooth and ſweet Oratours to pleade for the maintaining of ſinne, and all our hands like ſtout ſouldiers and couragious Champions to fight in the defence of ſinne. Thus have we waged and managed warre againſt thee our God, ever ſince we were borne, ſo that now thou maiſt juſtly ſpue us out of thy mouth, cut us off in the midſt of our ſinnes, come amongſt us this very preſent, and binde us hand and foot, and at the end of theſe few and miſerable dayes ſend us all into hell together, that ſo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan might pay us our wages onely, whom thus long we have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed and ſerved: thus emptying our ſelves from all truſt and confidence in the arme of fleſh, we fly unto thee O God, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of our hope, and the tower built for our defence, with many deepe ſighes and groanes from our perplexed conſciences and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſed ſoules, moſt humbly intreating thee to be gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to all our ſinnes, for they are wondrous great, make it thy glory to paſſe by and to winke at them; poure into our ſoules the oyle of thy mercies, ſupple our hard and dry hearts with the ſweete influence of thy beſt graces, and cure all our ſwelling wounds with the true balme of <hi>Gilead;</hi> purge (good Lord) and cleanſe all the polluted and infected corners of our hearts, that though at this day our ſinnes be as olde as <hi>Adam,</hi> as numberleſſe as the ſtarres of heaven, as high as the talleſt Cedars in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Lord plucke them up by the rootes, bury them in everlaſting forgetfulneſſe, that they may never ſtoppe the iſſue of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, nor draw downe upon us the vialls of thy wrath, nor be a wound and griefe to our troubled conſciences in this life, or
<pb facs="tcp:173660:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> worke deſpaire in us at the end of our dayes; nor ſtand up in judgement to be the utter ruine and condemnation of our ſoules and bodies at the laſt day. Good Lord prepare us all for a better life, fit us all for the kingdome of thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, guide us all with thy bleſſed Spirit, tutor us out of thy holy word, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us by thy mercifull corrections, and by thy fatherly bleſſings, wed our affections, and knit our hearts more neere unto thee in newneſſe of life, than ever heretofore they have beene: that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as becommeth thy obedient children and ſervants an holy and a religious remnant of our dayes, we may by thy grace and mercy be partakers of a joyfull and a comfortable death, and after death of a glorious reſurrection to everlaſting life &amp; peace among thy Saints. Neither do we pray to thee for our ſelves only, but for all people and Nations of the earth, but more particularly for the place in which we live, and therin according to our bounden duty for thy ſervant &amp; our Soveraign, <hi>Charles,</hi> by thy ſpecial providence King of <hi>Great Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the moſt true, Ancient, Catholicke and Apoſtolike faith, and in all cauſes, and over all perſons within theſe his Majeſties Realmes and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions next under thee and thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus ſupreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, adde unto his dayes, as thou didſt unto the dayes of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> that he may enjoy a long and a proſperous reigne over us; and in the meane time remember him in goodneſſe for the good he hath done already to thy Church. Beſtow the ſweeteſt of thy bleſſings upon our gracious Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> our hopefull Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe royall branches beyond the ſeas, ſeaſon them in their young and tender yeares with thy feare, that they may be great in thy favour: and if it may ſtand with thine eternall Decree, let us never want a holy and a religious man of that houſe and line to governe the ſcepters of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and to maintaine the preaching of thy glorious Goſpell within theſe his Majeſties Realmes and Dominions ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endures. Bleſſe our King with an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, valiant and a religious Councell and Nobility, bleſſe him with a learned, painfull, and a zealous Clergy, by what names or titles ſoever they be called, whether they be Arch-Biſhops, or Biſhops, and all other painfull labourers in this thy Vineyard: bleſſe him with a wiſe, prudent, and a religious Gentry: bleſſe him
<pb facs="tcp:173660:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> with a peaceable, a loyall and a religious Commonalty, and good God we beſeech thee to ſhower downe thy bleſſings upon the right hand and upon the left to them whom it hath pleaſed thee to ſend to this Congregation, that by the bleſſing of thy good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit whenſoever they ſhall ſtand on thy Mountaine to deliver a Meſſage from thee, give them good Father, (what wilt thou give them?) give them wiſe and underſtanding hearts, that they may open to thy people the wondrous things of thy law; good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther touch their tongues with a coale from thy holy Altar, that by the bleſſing of thy holy Spirit they may be able to worke ſome holineſſe in the hearts of a ſinfull and unbeleeving people: and cut downe the head and ſtrength of ſome ſinne that remaineth in us: and to this end and purpoſe make them ſound in thy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, terrible in thy threatnings ſweet in thy comforts, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and effectuall in all thy perſwaſions; and mercifull Father make thy word like the bow of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and like the ſword of <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Gideon,</hi> that never returned empty from the blood of the ſlaine, and the fat of the mighty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we come unto thee for our ſelves againe thy moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervants, that are here aſſembled in a reverent feare of thy moſt holy and bleſſed name, moſt humbly intreating thee in Ieſus Chriſt to be gracious and mercifull to all our ſinnes, and to be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually preſent with thy bleſſed Spirit in the midſt of us all, and grant that thy word may drop and diſtill upon our tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, like raine upon the mowen graſſe, and as dew comes down from heaven to water the earth; take away the ſcales of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from all blind and dark underſtandings, remove farre from us all lets and hinderances whereby the bleſſed ſeed of thy word hath bin to many and ſundry times made unfruitfull in the hearts of ſinfull and unbelieving people: and to every ſoule that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in thy houſe this day, or at any other time, grant us all holy diligence to ſeeke thee, godly wiſdome to know thee, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied underſtanding to finde thee aright; that ſo thy word may prove the ſweet ſavour of life unto everlaſting life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Saviour; in whoſe moſt holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed name we are bold to conclude theſe our weake and imperfect prayers in that perfect forme of prayer which Chriſt hath taught us, ſaying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173660:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DIRECTION FOR MAGISTRATES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EXOD. 18. Chap. Verſe 21.</bibl>
                  <p>Moreover, provide thou among all the people, men of courage, fearing God, men dealing truly, hating covetouſneſſe, and appoint ſuch over them to be Rulers over thouſands, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over hundreds, Rulers over fifties, and Rulers over tennes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are in the body naturall three principall members, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the heart, and the braine, reſembling three principal mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the body politicke, the Magiſtrate, the Phyſitian, and the Divine. The liver is the beginning of naturall faculties, ſegregates the humours, ingenders ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173660:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> blood, and by veines ſends it into the body of man from noxious humours, whereby it may be indangered, and preſcribes wholeſome diet, whereby it may be preſerved and kept in health. The heart is the beginning of vitall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, generates vitall ſpirits, ſends them into eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular member: Like to this is the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, for hee is <hi>Principium,</hi> though not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of generation, nor <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Radication, yet to uſe the word of the Anatomiſt, he is <hi>Principium</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of diſpenſation of the vitall ſpirits, hee takes a man where the Phyſitians leave him, makes him of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to bee a ſpirituall man, tranſformes him from a meere man to be a pure Saint. The braine is the beginning of animall faculties, chiefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the body, ſits in the higheſt roome, as in her royall pallace, compaſſed about with the <hi>Cranium,</hi> the <hi>Pericranium,</hi> and the two <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges,</hi> which are like ſtrong Caſtles and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termures againſt forraigne invaſion; it hath the five externall ſenſes as intelligencers, to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice what is done abroad, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe, he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy, the underſtandings privy counſellors, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory as regiſter &amp; book of records, yet the brain is not idle, but buſied in tempering the ſpirits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the heart, ſending them by nerves into the old body, and thereby giving ſenſe and motion to each part: And this braine is the fit embleme of a good Magiſtrate, who as he hath forts and guards, and Counſellours, and records,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173660:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo muſt he know that he hath them not for his owne uſe, but for the benefit of the body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique; and therefore muſt beſtirre himſelfe in tempering the ſpirits received from the heart, I meane in making uſe of ſpirituall counſells recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Miniſter of the Goſpell. Now as the body Naturall is in beſt eſtate when all theſe three are well affected, but very ill at eaſe if there be a diſtemper or dyſcracie in any of them; ſo in the body Politique, if the Phyſitian, the Divine, and the Magiſtrate, be faithfull in their places, and follow the rule of their bookes, there would be no complaining in our ſtreetes: But if the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian inſtead of wholeſome Phyſicke, miniſter nothing but hemlocke; the Divine in ſtead of wholeſome Doctrine broach nothing but hereſie and curioſity; the Magiſtrate turne juſtice into wormewood: then is the head ſicke, and the heart heavie, and in the Symptomes of death upon the whole body, once more. Of all parts in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Naturall the braine is moſt ſubject unto diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of all parts in the body Politique the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate moſt obnoxious to ſlips and falls. Firſt, becauſe he hath many provocations which others want. Secondly, he wants a benefit which others have, he is not freely reproved, as others are. Thirdly, becauſe of thoſe <hi>Cubiculares Conſiliarij,</hi> as <hi>Lypſius</hi> calleth them, <hi>Politic. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tineae et Sorices Palatij,</hi> theſe rattes and mothes of the Court that feede upon other mens wants, live by other mens loſſes; and as the common ſouldier, in <hi>Tacitus in Pompeium, Miſeriâ noſtrâ magnus es,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:173660:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> grow great by others mens miſeries, who ſell their Maſters favours, as <hi>Zoticus</hi> in <hi>Lampridius</hi> ſolde the faire promiſes of <hi>Heliogabolus;</hi> and are alwayes ready for their owne advantage to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud their Maſters worſt and baſeſt actions.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that <hi>Iethro</hi> gives this good directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Iudges and Magiſtrates which thou doeſt appoint muſt be men of courage, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, dealing truly, hating covetouſneſſe. Which words have in them, 1. A <hi>Quis,</hi> 2. A <hi>Quos,</hi> 3. A <hi>Quibus.</hi> The <hi>Quis</hi> is <hi>Moſes, Sed conſulto Domino,</hi> and gives this concluſion, that the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Iudges and Magiſtrates is of God. In the beginning of time the Lord preſcribed to the heavens their courſes and motions, and they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; to the Elements he ſet bounds and limits, and they keepe them; the bees he gave a King, ſaith <hi>Elian de hist. animal. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. and they obey him; to man hee gave lawes, and hee tranſgreſſed them, wrote them in his heart, and man blotted them out. Againe, whenſoever the Heathen made lawes, they were wont to father them upon ſome of their gods, thereby to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe credit and reverence: When <hi>Licurgus</hi> made lawes for the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> he fathered them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Apollo: Minos</hi> for the <hi>Cretians,</hi> he fathered them upon <hi>Iupiter, Solon,</hi> and <hi>Draco:</hi> For the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians,</hi> they fathered them upon the Goddeſſe <hi>Minerva,</hi> as <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> reports of them. When <hi>Numa</hi> made lawes for the <hi>Romans,</hi> he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them upon the Goddeſſe <hi>Egraecia,</hi> as <hi>Plut.</hi> in the life of <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> reports. When <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacharſis</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173660:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Scythian</hi> Philoſopher made lawes for the <hi>Scythians,</hi> hee fathered them upon <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molxis,</hi> as <hi>Vives</hi> upon <hi>Aug.</hi> and <hi>Herodotus</hi> in his <hi>Melpomene</hi> have related: but all this could not refraine wilfull man from exorbitancy and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt riot againſt God. It is true of him which the olde <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> ſaid of the olde <hi>Athenians,</hi> they knew what was to be done, but did it not; and which the <hi>Cimickin Laertius</hi> objected to the Philoſophers of <hi>Greece,</hi> they had good lawes, but practiſed them not, they made no more account of lawes than <hi>Remus</hi> in <hi>Livie, dec.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriding the walls which <hi>Romulus</hi> had built, hee ſtood in no more awe than the frogges in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of leaping over the jawes of the lion, when he was couchant and faſt aſleepe; and therefore did God appoint the Magiſtrate to put life into this dead letter, and made him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> calls him, <hi>Ethi. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. a living law, that theſe two, the Law and the Magiſtrate, the one as a ſword, the other as a ſouldier to draw it, the one as a ſoveraigne medicine, the other as a Phyſitian to apply it, the one as a pibble gathered out of the ſtreame, the other as a skilfull <hi>David</hi> to ſling it, might unite the forces to the utter extirpation of idolatry, the protection of juſtice, the ſupporting of ſound religion, the diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſinne: and this is the authority they have from God.</p>
            <p>In which point wee muſt with <hi>Tully</hi> diſtinguiſh the power it ſelfe. Secondly, the meanes of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining. Thirdly, the manner of execution. The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173660:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt is allwayes of God, but not the ſecond nor the third; <hi>Potestatem Deus diſtribuit,</hi> God gives the power. <hi>Elationem potentiae malitiam venit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregor.</hi> as he is quoted by the ordinary gloſſe; If the Magiſtrate be good, he is ſet there for the good of the people, if wicked, he is ſet there for the ſinne of the people; <hi>Saul</hi> is appointed by God as well as <hi>David, Nero</hi> as well as <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and <hi>Aſhur</hi> as well as <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> But the one is ſtirred up to be the Saviour of the people, as <hi>Ehud</hi> was, <hi>Iud.</hi> 3.15. the other as the rod of his wrath, as <hi>Aſhur</hi> was: <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.23. Kings ſhall be thy nurſing fathers, and Queenes thy nurſes: Nor from Chriſt, who commands to giue unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> that which is due unto him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. nor from <hi>Peter,</hi> who bids honour the King, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2: 27. nor from <hi>Paul,</hi> who bids pray for Kings and Magiſtrates, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2: 2. nor from <hi>Moſes,</hi> who commands not to raile upon the Iudge, nor ſpeake evill of the ruler of the people, <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.28. It is true of them which God ſaid to <hi>Samuell</hi> concerning the Iewes, when they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked their preſent government, they have not caſt away thee, but they have caſt away mee, that I ſhould not rule over them, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Papiſt, who denies not temporall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of our Kings and Iudges, yet tyes one of the Magiſtrates hands, leſſens his authority, and limits him only <hi>ad Temporalia,</hi> and for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall matters, he hath no more to doe with them than <hi>Vzzah</hi> had to touch the Arke, who for his paines was ſtriken with death. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7. hee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173660:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> dares not denie but Magiſtrates be gods, for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſhould confute him; <hi>I have ſaid yee are gods. Pſa.</hi> 82. but yet ſay of them as the <hi>Aramite</hi> ſaid of the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that he was <hi>the God of the Mountaines, not of the Vallies,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 20.28. they be gods and governours of the Laitie, not of the Clergie; For the Councell of <hi>Constance: Seſſ.</hi> 31. <hi>Laicus in clericum iuriſdictionem non habet.</hi> The Councell of <hi>Trent. Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Perſonarum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticarum immunitas adeò instituitur: Beller. lib: de eler: cap.</hi> 28. <hi>clerici non poſſunt à iudice politico puniri, nec ſunt Reges Clericorum ſuperiores, idque habuit iure divino.</hi> The exemption is by a divine right, ſaith the ſame Cardinall gainſt <hi>Berclay. cap.</hi> 34. quite contrary to the order and courſe of Scripture, for <hi>David</hi> had the ſame power over the high Prieſts that Kings have over their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and calls <hi>Zadoc</hi> the Prieſt and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet his ſervants, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1. <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne turned <hi>Abiathar</hi> out of the Prieſthood, that the word of the Lord might be fulfilled which was ſpoken againſt the houſe of <hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 2.27. Which text hath ſo puzled <hi>Bell.</hi> writing againſt <hi>Berclay,</hi> that hee is glad to confeſſe that in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> time Prieſts were ſubject unto Kings: <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus ſolvit &amp;c. Math:</hi> 17, 24, 25. <hi>Paul</hi> appealed <hi>ad Caeſarem, non ad Petrum,</hi> and he hath warrant, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.11, when Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> expounded that of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. ſpeaketh thus &amp;c. conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to this is <hi>Tert: lib. de Idela: cap.</hi> 15. and St. <hi>Bernard ad Archiepiſcopum Senonenſem Epiſt:</hi> 42. <hi>Si omnis anima et iam et veſtra quis vos accepit ab
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173660:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> vniverſitate, ſi quis tentat excipere conatur decipere.</hi> For concluſion note, onely how <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this point hath contradicted himſelfe in writing againſt <hi>Barclay, cap.</hi> 34. his poſition is, <hi>Clerici ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empti ſunt non ſolum privilegijs Principum, ſed jure divino:</hi> and yet in his 1 <hi>Lib. Eccleſiae de membris militantis,</hi> intituled <hi>De Clericis cap.</hi> 28. <hi>Nullum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt deferri Dei verbum quo iſta Clericorum exceptio confirmetur: Propoſ.</hi> 4. In the firſt skirmiſh he is like to <hi>Thraſilius</hi> in <hi>Anthonies Deipnoſoph lib.</hi> 12. challengeth every page of Scripture to be their advocate, that if it were poſſible for paper and inke to bluſh, his bookes would be as red as his Bonnet, and at the parting he is willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that there is no expreſſe precept of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for it. I end with the ſpeech of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, noted by <hi>Theodoret, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. when he exiled <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nicomedia, Si quis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum in conſulto tumultuatur meae authoritati illius audacia coarcebitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be Gods prerogative to appoint Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, what may we thinke of them that would wring this power from God, and caſt it upon him that ſits in the Temple and advanceth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe above all that is called God, making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the King of all other Kings, to whom all Kings and Kingdomes muſt doe homage and pay tribute, the greateſt Monarchs muſt fall downe and kiſſe the feete of his Holineſſe, as they ſay their bookes <hi>Sacrarum Ceremoniarum, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. The Emperour muſt hold his ſtirrop when he mounteth, the bridle when he lighteth, beare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173660:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> his traine when he walketh, holde the baſon when he waſheth; he now acts the ſame part that the Divell acted, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.9. and takes upon him as he did to diſpoſe of all the Kingdomes of the earth; and we may ſay of him as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaid of the Divell, <hi>Mentitur Diabolus, nam cujus juſſu ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines creantur, illius juſſu regna constituuntur.</hi> Who knowes not that <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt was deprived of his Kingdome by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, as <hi>Petrus Iuſtinianus</hi> reports in his <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Rerum venatarum: Fredericke</hi> the 2. by <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 4. <hi>Leo</hi> the 3. called <hi>Leo Iſauros</hi> was by <hi>Gregory</hi> the 3. firſt excommunicate, and then deprived of all his revenues in <hi>Italy,</hi> becauſe he commanded that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſhould be pulled downe in their Churches, as <hi>Carion</hi> in 3. of his <hi>Chro.</hi> in the life of <hi>Leo</hi> the 3. That <hi>Paul</hi> the 2. in the beginning of his life a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Pedler, as <hi>Platina</hi> calls him, at the end ſtrangled by the Divell in the act of Sodomie, as <hi>Melancton lib.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 913. deprived <hi>George</hi> the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and ſtirred up the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia</hi> to make warre againſt him, as <hi>Omiphrius</hi> ſaith of him, and for no other reaſon but becauſe he favoured the doctrine of <hi>Iohn Huſse,</hi> as <hi>Bonfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Rer: Hung: Dec:</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the 2. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived the King of <hi>Caſtile.</hi> Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. tooke away the <hi>East Indies</hi> from the true owner, and gave it to the <hi>Luſitanians;</hi> the <hi>West,</hi> and gave it to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that <hi>Atabalippa</hi> might juſtly challenge, but all in vaine: <hi>Quid monſtri eſset iste Papa qui ſic daret non ſua?</hi> as <hi>Montinaeus de tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali pontij monarchia, cap.</hi> 5. That <hi>Pius</hi> the 5. as <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:173660:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> at the yeare 1569. tooke away this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from the late Queene, and gave it to <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> That <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. deprived <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the 3. of <hi>France,</hi> firſt of his Kingdome, and then of his life: I omit the wrongs to <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. they are noted by <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> at the yeare 1170. to have beene ſo ſhamefull, that <hi>Matchaivell</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſt. Florent.</hi> ſeemes to ſcorne him for it. <hi>Rex his flagellis tergum ſubjecit, quorum hodie puderit quemlibet privatum.</hi> And when King <hi>Iohn</hi> complained, <hi>Romanis artibus emunxi Anglos argento: Pope Innocentius</hi> the third tooke away his Kingdome, and gave it to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> at the yeare 215. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell not that the Pope would faine have footing in <hi>England,</hi> which <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 4. called <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum delitiarum, puteum vero inexhauſtum.</hi> Who would not deſire to have ſuch a garden, who would not wiſh ſuch a well as that? The Poets feigne, that the River <hi>Arethuſa</hi> being ſuddenly ſwallowed up into the ground, runnes quite through the ſea, and riſeth againe in <hi>Cicily.</hi> But without feigning, from <hi>England</hi> as from a well hath ſprung golden rivers, which being ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwallowed up did runne through the ſea, and riſe againe at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Popes Exchequer. But I marvell why Prieſts and Ieſuites will bee his Factours, whom hee uſeth as a fiſher uſeth little fiſhes to catch great ones, hee fiſheth with Prieſts and Ieſuites as baites to catch Kings and Princes, and Kingdomes. I remember a fable of the Ape, ſeeing a Cheſnut in the fire, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173660:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowing not how to get it, ſpied a Spaniell by the fire-ſide, and ſuddenly catcht his foote to take out the cheſnut: wherein theſe men may ſee their faces in a homely glaſſe. The golden Supremacy is the cheſnut, perills and dangers the fire; the Pope loath his owne fingers, uſeth them as the Spaniells foote to ſcrape forth the cheſnut: little cares hee how they be ſcorched, ſo he be in hope to obtaine his deſire; and though many of them have burnt both their hands and hearts, yet bleſſed be God he miſt the cheſnut. Wee have heard the roaring of his Bulls, but they have not hurt us, they have beene like the ſhewes of <hi>Semiramis</hi> the <hi>Aſtrian</hi> Queene, when ſhee warred againſt the King of <hi>India,</hi> which ſeemed afarre off to be Elephants and Dromeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but being examined were nothing elſe but hides of oxen ſtuft with ſtraw; ſuch have beene all Popiſh machinations againſt us. They have plotted, but God hath prevented them, laid ſnares, but God hath broken them; attended miſchiefe, but God hath confounded them: <hi>Nati natorum &amp; qui naſcentur ab illis,</hi> the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are yet unborne have continuall cauſe to remember what the Lord hath done for us; let our tongues cleave unto the roofe of our mouthes, let the Sunne deny us his light, the heavens their influence, the earth her fruites, if wee forget to give God thankes, and to ſay as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124. <hi>If the Lord had not beene on our ſide, they had ſwallowed us up quicke, when their wrath was kindled against us, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:173660:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> and this I paſſe over and come to a two fold du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The one concernes our duty to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, the other, the Magiſtrates dutie towards God.</p>
            <p>Our duty to you is reverence and honour <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle:</hi> and <hi>Herodotus</hi> in <hi>Euterpe,</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded a ſtory of <hi>Amaſis</hi> the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who being mocked of his Subjects, by reaſon of his meane diſcent, tooke a golden baſon wherein they vſed to waſh their feete, and turned it into the Image and ſimilitude of one of their gods: and the men that before regarded it not, did then fall downe and worſhip it. The ſtory applies it ſelfe, though when you were private men your reſpect was ordinary, but the Lord hath given you his owne name: <hi>I have ſaid you are gods,</hi> and ſet you in his owne place of judgement, and truſted you in his worke, the cauſe and lives of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; we obey and reverence you even for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, and this is our duty towards you.</p>
            <p>The next is the Magiſtrates dutie towards God: God hath given you much, and he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth much from you, and yet ſometimes it comes to paſſe that they pay him leaſt who owe him moſt. <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports of <hi>Claudius</hi> that he was a good ſubject, but a bad Emperour; and in his <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> of <hi>Titus,</hi> that he was a bad privat man, but a good Emperour; But where one proves like <hi>Titus,</hi> bad private men, and good governours; a thouſand prove like <hi>Claudius,</hi> good private men, but bad governours. As Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> ſaid of <hi>Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine</hi> the Metropolitane Biſhop of this Kingdome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173660:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he was <hi>Monachus ferventiſſimus, Abbas calidus, Epiſcopus tepidus, Archiepiſcopus remiſſus.</hi> or as <hi>Bucolcerus</hi> at the yeare 1464. reports of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus Silvius,</hi> that after he got the Popedome and changed his name into <hi>Pius Secundus,</hi> he then condemned many things which before he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: whereupon one wittily plaies upon him thus, <hi>Quod Aenaeas probavit, Pius damnavit.</hi> It was the practiſe of heathen perſecutors, to place the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Venus,</hi> in the ſame place, where Chriſt was crucified, that if any came there to worſhip, they might ſeeme to worſhip <hi>Venus.</hi> A tricke which the Devill uſeth at this day, to ſet in Gods roome and ſeate of judgement an Idoll Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, ſometimes a <hi>Cupid,</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> delighting in pleaſure, ſometimes a <hi>Mars,</hi> delighting in blood, ſometimes a <hi>Mercurie,</hi> with a voyce like <hi>Iacob,</hi> to ſpeak ſmoothly, but hands like <hi>Eſau,</hi> and fingers like lyme-twiggs, to bring all home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and make their places but bands for their profits. And howſoever this point may ſeeme as needleſſe, as for <hi>Phormio</hi> to diſcourſe of mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Diſcipline before <hi>Hanniball;</hi> yet I beſeech you beare with patience, for though I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you, I muſt not forget my ſelfe, nor my place, nor the mount whereon I ſtand. For I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo am in Gods roome, and am ſet here to put you in mind of your duty: your maine dutie is the care of religion and worſhip of God, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Idolatry, and prophanes. There are a kinde of men whereof I may ſay as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Catelinarians, Semper prohibetur, ſemper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinetur,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:173660:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> wee have lawes againſt them, and yet ſtill wee keepe them: a good common wealth conſiſting of <hi>Heterogeniall</hi> parts, muſt be like <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſheet in the 10. of the <hi>Acts.</hi> wherein though there bee all manner of beaſts, and foules; yet muſt it bee knit at the foure corners: though in a common wealth there be Nobles flying above, like the foules of the heauen, and meaner men creeping below, yet muſt it be knit at the foure corners, the remoteſt parts as lines in a center, muſt meete in unity of religion; if you be ſlacke in this, it is no ſmall danger whereto our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may be quickly brought. <hi>Seneca</hi> on <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> reports, that <hi>Cadmus</hi> the King of <hi>Phaenicia</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of his followers ſtaine by a ſerpent, ſlew the ſerpent, and ſowed the teeth of it; <hi>Ex quibus prodiere homines armati:</hi> and we have good cauſe to feare it, though ſome of theſe ſerpents brood be dead, yet there be armed men bred out of their bones, who though they may ſpeake us faire, yet I approve the judgement of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who ſtood more afraid of <hi>Brutus,</hi> who had his mouth in his heart, than of <hi>Anthony,</hi> who had his heart in his mouth. Our land never was ſo ſicke, never groaned ſo loud, never mourned in ſuch a paſſion, never travelled of ſuch <hi>Hermaphrodites</hi> with halfe ſo much paine and griefe, as now it doth; ſhee hath already bred, and at this day both feedeth, and clotheth numberleſſe ſwarmes of outcaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, who ſometimes like <hi>Iudas</hi> pretend to kiſſe, but if they can come neare enough, intend to kill her; ſhe may conclude a peace with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173660:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> enemies, but they will cut her throat by way of friendſhip: It is no whiſpering rumour, but the voice of truth, but they are warmely lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and richly friended, and coſtly fed, with the marrow and fatneſſe of our land, who in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of our Iubiles make flawes in our peace, and in the midſt of our joyes indanger our lives; and if ever forraigner ſhould invade our Land, would lend their knives to cut our throates, and be the foremoſt men to beare armes againſt us: this alas, this is the malady that makes the viſage of our Church ſo wanne, and her face ſo full of wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, her backe ſo full of furrowes, and her eyes ſo full of teares, and her heart ſo full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, that though many good Phyſitians will ſpeake her faire, and wiſh her health, yet they launch not the Impoſtume, they purge not the fretting humour that conſumes and grieves her; you may reade in her face that the gripings and convulſions are unſufferable; you may heare by her groanes, that her paines are intollerable; you may preſage by her pulſes the ſignes and Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of deſolation and death: And when theſe Catholicke vipers have broken her heart, what will become of us, who ſuffer ſuch profeſſours, as will never proove good ſubjects to varniſh their neſts, and make their bowers within her. It would doe them good to do us hurt, it would lengthen their lives to ſhorten ours, it would bring them halfe way to heaven, to bury their poniards in our breaſts, it would make a newe feaſt, and another holiday in the <hi>Romane</hi> Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173660:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> if they might ſmell the burning, or heare tell of the ſmoake and aſhes of our Churches, they are already become ſo bold, their number ſo exceeding great, their religion ſo bloudy, their malice ſo inveterate, that if no ſharper courſe be taken to repreſſe and ſmother them, they will adventure within a while, to trie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we or they ſhall be the Maſters; and if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther malice, or multitude can doe it, they will make bonefires of our fleſh, they will cut off our lives, and confiſcate our livings, and ſet fire on our Churches, and martyr our Cleargie, and maſſacre our Iudges, and murther our Princes; and ſay of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Edome</hi> did of <hi>Ieruſalem, downe with it, downe with it, even to the ground.</hi> And if ever this day of mourning come upon us, which I pray God may never come, wee may thanke our ſelves for keeping ſuch <hi>Romiſh</hi> waſpes in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hives.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">The Second part of the Text.</note> I come now to the ſecond part of the Text, The <hi>Quos,</hi>(<hi>viz.</hi> The perſons whom he muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point:) and theſe are deſcribed, firſt generally, The Magiſtrate muſt be a choiſe man, one of a thouſand, culled and ſelected out of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Secondly, He is deſcribed by his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar properties, and theſe are 4. Firſt, they muſt be <hi>Viri potentes,</hi> powerfull and able men. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, They muſt be, <hi>viri timentes Deum,</hi> Such as feare God. Thirdly, They muſt be, <hi>viri a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes veritatem,</hi> ſuch as love trueth. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>viri abhorrentes avaritiam,</hi> ſuch as hate cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. Of theſe in order.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:173660:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And firſt of the generall, hee muſt be choſen out of all the people, he muſt be a ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> man. It is the obſervation of <hi>Abulenſis,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the high Prieſts out of all the people of <hi>Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 17. It is the obſervation of <hi>Pelargus,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſummoned by death to reſigne his place, <hi>nec filios obtrudit ſuos, nec populum in ſuffragia mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit,</hi> he ſhuffles not in one of his ſonnes, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it to moſt voices, but deſires God to appoint and nominate ſome one whom he had ſingularly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with his ſpirit, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. <hi>David,</hi> a man culled out of all the ſonnes of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. the twelve Apoſtles pickt and choſen out of all the Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.13. Were the birds of the ayre to chuſe them a governour, it ſhould be the Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix; were the ſtarres of the heaven to chuſe them a governour, it ſhould be the Sunne; were the trees of the forreſt to chuſe a governour, it ſhould be the Cedar; were the flowers of the garden to chuſe them a governour, it ſhould be the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the fragrant Roſe.</p>
            <p>We muſt obſerve the rule of <hi>Paris</hi> King of <hi>Troy,</hi> when <hi>Pallas Iuno,</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> contended for the golden apple, <hi>Detur digniori,</hi> let the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous have it: the Magiſtrate ſhould be like a poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy made of the choyceſt flowers, or like the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Helena</hi> that <hi>Zeuxes</hi> made in the Temple of the <hi>Croconians,</hi> whatſoever was faire and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in any other, was admirably compoſed and wrought in that one. <hi>St. Auguſt. De Civit. Dei, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. ſayes, the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> built their Temple of vertue directly in the way to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173660:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of honour, to ſignifie that it was not for a man to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pe to a ſeate of honour, before he had proceeded in the ſchoole of vertue.</p>
            <p>Hence I might juſtly challenge the precipitant forwardneſſe of ſome, who boldly intrude into places of eminence, both in Church and State, though it be well enough knowne that they are as eminent for their imperfections, as they are for their places: and the injurious dealings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who ſet Idols in the roome of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre unworthy perſons, who come little ſhort of <hi>Calligula,</hi> who was ſo in love with his horſe <hi>Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus,</hi> that he gave him his provender in a golden charger, made his horſe a Prieſt, and ſolemnly promiſed to make him a Conſul. But the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall will be manifeſt, if we take view of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular properties, whereof the firſt is, they muſt be <hi>viri potentes,</hi> able men, <hi>non corporis fortitudine, ſed animi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ferus:</hi> If the eye of a Iudge be not be not like sn Eagle, his hand like a Ladies; if the heart of a Iudge be not like a lyon, he is not fit to be Gods ſword-bearer, he muſt have a Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons heart, who cuts the wound, weepe the patient never ſo bitterly. <hi>Plorat ſecandus, &amp; ſecatur, plorat urendus, &amp; uritur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aug. in Mat. Ser.</hi> 15. &amp; this is not cruelty but mercy; for <hi>ſevit in vulnus, ut homo ſanetur, ſi palpetur vulnus, homo perditur.</hi> It was Gods ſpeech to <hi>Ioſhua, Be thou ſtrong and of good courage, Ioſh.</hi> 10. the commendation that the Angel gave <hi>Gideon, The Lord is with thee thou vàli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant man, Iudg.</hi> 6.8. I am of the opinion of <hi>Chabrias</hi> in the hiſtory, if you be lyons, let all the reſt of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173660:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the people be timerous hearts, we ſhall doe well; let all the reſt of the army be lyons, if you be timerous hearts, nothing can be well. O then awake and put on courage, you that miniſter judgement, me thinkes God ſpeakes to you as <hi>Gideon</hi> did to his men of warre in the ſeventh of <hi>Iudges,</hi> If you be timerous and fearefull, depart from Mount <hi>Gilead,</hi> and lay no hands upon your ſwords; you muſt remember that as the royall throne of <hi>Salomon</hi> whereon he ſate to judge was ſupported by lyons on both ſides, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.20. ſo when you ſit in ſeates of judgement, which is as the throne of <hi>Salomon,</hi> bee ſupported by the lyon-like vertues of courage and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; you muſt not tranſgreſſe for feare or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, therefore you have neede of courage; to ſilence the mighty, therefore you have neede of courage; to reſcue the poore out of the hands of the oppreſſours, with as much danger as <hi>David</hi> reſcued his ſilly lambe out of the mouth of the lyon and the beare, therefore you have neede of courage: you muſt with <hi>Zeileucus</hi> King of the <hi>Locrenſes,</hi> paſſe ſentence upon your owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren if they be found worthy of death, therefore you have neede of courage; you muſt confute the ſinnes of the mighty, you muſt ſupport the worke of the Miniſtery, you muſt be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving law, to helpe the poore to their right that ſuffer wrong, to heare the widowes cauſe, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the innocent <hi>Ioſephs</hi> and <hi>Ieremies,</hi> whom ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and revenge hath caſt into priſon, &amp; ſhut faſt into the ſtockes, and therefore you have neede of courage.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:173660:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt chuſe Iudges that doe feare God, nothing more needfull then this. I may ſay of it as <hi>Aristotle</hi> of Iuſtice: <hi>Eth; lib.</hi> 5. He that hath this vertue wants none, and without this, what is the Magiſtrate, but <hi>flagellum piorum, &amp; captivus vitiorum,</hi> one that Iudges others, and is ſinnes priſoner, himſelfe? without the feare of God, what is he? one that quarters his coate with Princes, and wants the badge of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie upon it: without this feare what is he? one that ſitts with Kings on earth, but hath not ſo much as a pew in heaven: without this feare, what is he? An heire of faire and goodly poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but a common pandor of foule and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vices: Without this feare, what is he? An <hi>Ahab,</hi> to reave away poore <hi>Naboths</hi> Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: a <hi>Pilate</hi> to condemne the innocent: a <hi>Saul,</hi> to torment the Saints, a <hi>Veſpatian</hi> to ſqueaze men like ſpunges: a <hi>Gehazi,</hi> to pocket up Talents of gold: a <hi>Bremus,</hi> to let deſolation into the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: In a word, without this feare, what is he? A perverter of Iuſtice, a receiver of falſe witnes, a Patrone of violence. Not like <hi>Zabulon,</hi> a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for weather beaten ſhippes: But like <hi>Dan,</hi> a <hi>Serpent</hi> in the way, and like <hi>Beniamin,</hi> a raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Wolfe:</hi> And as <hi>Paul</hi> cald <hi>Ananias,</hi> a whited wall. <hi>Act:</hi> 23.3.</p>
            <p>But how glorious the name, how beautifull the feete, how welcome the comming, how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious the admonitions, how ſtraight and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall the proceedings, how joyfull the widdow, how glad the innocent, how happy the land, from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173660:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> when valiant <hi>Othniels,</hi> valiant <hi>Gideons,</hi> incorrupt <hi>Samuels,</hi> in whom God hath planted his feare, be placed over us, to judge the people: Then is the Iudge wiſe to diſcerne right from wrong, and to finde out the hidden Myſteries of injquity, for God reveales ſecrets to them that feare him, and they have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of underſtanding. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14: then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to reſolve better then <hi>Criſippus: Si Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tè non geſſero, Deo diſplicebo, ſi rectè ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t neutrum volo:</hi> If I be not upright, I diſpleaſe God; if I bee upright, then I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe men, therefore I will doe neither, for the feare of God takes away all deſire of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10. Then he judges others, as one that remembers he muſt be judged himſelfe: meates unto others, as he that lookes that God ſhould meate unto him. Againe, then he helpes the Orphanes to their right: Then he lendes an eare to the widdowes cauſe, then he watcheth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his heart, that it receive no malice, over his eyes that they behold no wrong, over his eares, that they heare no falſe accuſation, over his tongue that it utter no unjuſt ſentence, over his hands, that they receive no bribes, over his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions that they ſway him not, over his humours that they draw him not, over his followers that they perſwade him not: then will he not be like <hi>Solons judge</hi> mentioned in <hi>Plut:</hi> to expound as he liſts, nor like <hi>Bonutian</hi> in <hi>Sueto,</hi> to puniſh the poore, and pardon the rich; he eſteemes not the judgement ſeate to be a golden harveſt, nor is he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173660:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> like a paire of ballance, to incline to that ſide which hath moſt weight, as <hi>Aeſchines</hi> ſometimes objected to <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> though he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a writ <hi>Ageſilus</hi> in <hi>Plut:</hi> ſent to one of his Iudges, <hi>Si inſons eſt dimitte, Sin minus mei cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa dimitte, utcunque dimitte:</hi> yet hee would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condemne the innocent, nor iuſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; if any ſparke of this holy feare be kindled in his heart by Gods holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>I will owe you the enlarging of the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: heare but a touch of the 4. and I will capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate your patience &amp; attention no longer. They muſt be <hi>viri abhorentes avaritiam,</hi> ſuch as hate co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſnes, that is the roote fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence all evills grow: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. and of all evils this is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that if a man be once infected with this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, he loves nothing, longs for nothing ſo much as that which increaſeth his malady &amp; ſicknes. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> compares him to a little hell, that will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſay it is enough. <hi>Auguſt. Evang. Quest. lib.</hi> 2. to the dropſie, whereof <hi>Ovid</hi> in his <hi>faſt. quo plus ſunt potae, plus ſitiuntur aquae: Salomon Prov:</hi> 30.15. to the two <hi>daughters</hi> of the <hi>horſe-leach,</hi> that is two forkes, ſhe hath under her tongue that be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatiate: <hi>non miſſura cutem niſi plena cruoris hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rudo. Iuven. Saty:</hi> 14: to a hote chimney ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely with that which ſets it on fire: or is like to a man that hath <hi>canium appetitum, ſitim non pellit niſi cauſa morbi:</hi> A ſinne which hath been oft ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, convicted, and condemned: but ſtill it makes ſhift, for reproofe or pardon, and is not yet executed; the effect of my ſpeech ſhall be that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173660:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> it may be cloſe priſoner, &amp; not appeare at this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſes, that it may not ſit on the bench, the Iudge muſt ſtoppe his eares, as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> did for feare of the 5 <hi>Syren</hi> charmes, and though a man ſhould come unto him as <hi>Iupiter</hi> came into <hi>Danae's</hi> lap, <hi>Per im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluvium aureu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> in a ſhewer of gold, he muſt have no welcome. And <hi>Lucian</hi> in <hi>Hermotinus</hi> commends the old <hi>Areopagites,</hi> that they judged their cauſes in the night time, that the Iudge might not ſee the gliſtering of gold.</p>
            <p>A man that hath a pearle in his eye, is preſently blinde, and knowes not which is the right way for him to walke in, if he be not led and guided, he ſtumbles at every blocke, and falls into every pit, and lives in continuall danger of his life: If Iudges have a rich pearle in their eyes, it quite blindes them, <hi>Excellens ſenſibile deſtruit ſenſum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Arist:</hi> 2. <hi>de anima.</hi> 12. ſuch bright objects will dazle them, that they cannot judge betweene right and wrong. I cannot approve that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenaeus, lib.</hi> 12. that juſtice ſhould have, &amp;c. I had rather approve and like her in her old por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture, as ſhee was painted by the olde Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, without eyes, and without hands; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eyes, to ſignifie that the Iudge ſhould not ſo much as looke upon golde to covet it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, to ſignifie that if never ſo much were offered, they ſhould not take it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tully Offic. lib.</hi> 3. remembers a ſaying of <hi>Caeſar</hi> borrowed from <hi>Euripides</hi> in his <hi>Phaenicia: Si vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landum eſt jus, violandum eſt regni cauſâ;</hi> if conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may be crackt, and juſtice caſt under hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for any thing, it is for reigning; but mine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173660:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> juſtly, <hi>violandum lucri cauſâ,</hi> if for any thing, it is for gaining: and therefore the Poets feigne, that when gold was digged out of the earth, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice tooke her ſelfe to her wings, and flew into heaven: firſt, <hi>Effodiuntur opes,</hi> and then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon it, <hi>Terras Aſtrae a reliquit.</hi> My hope is, that this impiety dares not pearke up to the bench, and I deſire that it may be kept from the barre alſo; if it may be permitted to ſpeake, it will make a Lawyer Phariſe-like to ſtraine at a gnat, and ſwallow a camell, to tithe mint and cummin, and play faſt and looſe with his tongue, as he liſt: a golden key commonly opens a wrong locke; <hi>Loquente auro nil pollet quaevis oratio.</hi> The mouth of a Lawyer, ſaith <hi>Tully,</hi> is an Oracle for the whole Citty, but if in this mouth there be a guilded tongue, it will prove like the Oracle at <hi>Delphos,</hi> whereof <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> complained in his time, that it did ſpeake nothing but what <hi>Philip</hi> would have it that had given a double fee. But I for my part accuſe no man, but many that have beene ancient Termers ſay, that Lawyers take much money and ſay little for it, that they come amongſt many of you for ſuccour, as a ſheepe runnes to the thornes and briars for ſhelter in time of a tempeſt, they are ſaved from the ſhower for that time, but that which ſaved the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pulls that wool from their backes, that they are never able to abide another ſtorme. Some have money for holding their peace, others for ſpeaking; that you who ſhould be like <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut, become like <hi>Clotho</hi> to ſpinne, and like <hi>Lacheſis</hi> to draw in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173660:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> length the thread of contention. <hi>Maginus</hi> and ſome other Geographers noting the diameter and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of the earth, are of opinion, that if a foote-man had a path round about the world, he might goe it in 900 dayes, and take no hard journeyes; a ſtrange thing that one man in that time ſhould goe through the world, and ſome other in twice ſo much time cannot paſſe through an Engliſh Court, or the length of <hi>Weſtminster</hi> hall: let it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be tolde in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſhed in the ſtreetes of <hi>Askelon,</hi> that Engliſh Lawyers ſhould grow great, as that common ſouldier in <hi>Tacitus</hi> tolde <hi>Pompey, per nostram miſeriam,</hi> by the miſery of poore clients: it is wickedneſſe inexpiable to build your houſes with the fall of others; let it never be ſaid that you are like the milt of a mans body, whereof <hi>Laurentius</hi> ſaith, that it never growes great until all other parts of the body de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay and periſh. But purge your hearts from cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires, waſh your hands fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ruſt of that ſilver, &amp; your conſciences from the canker of that gold which with greedineſſe you have conjeſted and raked together, know for certaine that God will ſtrictly examine, and your ſoules ſhall one day pay for it.</p>
            <p>When one asked <hi>Diogenes,</hi> what was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that golde alwayes looked pale, he ſhaped him this anſwer, <hi>Quia tot habet inſidiatores,</hi> becauſe ſo many crafty heads lie in ambuſh for it; I pray God you may all be more greedy of heaven than of earth, more willing to winne the ſtreight way to heaven, than the broad way to a heape of wealth:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173660:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> And more carefull to make your election, than your lands and poſſeſſions ſure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this ſinne is to be whipt from all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Witneſſes alſo; if you have but ſuch a thought of this, what ſhall I have? you ſhall be ſure to meete with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that will ſay, what ſhall I give? You muſt ſweare in truth and juſtice, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.2. You are to be whipt for ever out of the company of God and his Angels, you are to be ſhut out of the kingdome and inheritance of the Saints, you ſhall heare the thundering of an angry Iudge, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. There will be a writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, a flying booke, it is ten cubits broad, and twenty cubits long, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. and that booke is a curſe that flieth over the whole earth, verſe 3. that curſe ſhall lay ſiege to the walls and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your houſes, to conſume both you and them, if money make you ſpeake either more or leſſe than the truth. Such men, ſaith <hi>Diodo. Sicu. Bib. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> were alwayes puniſhed with death: and ſo <hi>Bohemus de moribus gent. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>ad Aug.</hi> in his <hi>Quae. in Deut. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. but that is but an eaſie puniſhment, and temporall, but the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God hath for you is endleſſe and eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, you ſhall ſtand without, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.15. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, without glory, without mercy, without comfort, without hope, without the Kingdome, you ſhall have your portion in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8. I therefore charge you in the name of God, as you will anſwer it at the dreadfull day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173660:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> and when you ſhall remember my words, and ſee my face againe, that not money nor money<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth make you ſmother the truth, or ſupport an ill cauſe; that you deale faithfully betwixt a man and his brother, that you remember the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Let not this ſinne be once named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you.</hi> A word for concluſion.</p>
            <p>Right Honorable, be you like <hi>Iethroes</hi> Iudges, men of courage to helpe poore ones, to defend weake ones, to oppoſe great ones, to cut off wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones: Like <hi>Iethroes</hi> Iudges fearing God, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God allwayes before your eyes, judging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if you were going to be judged your ſelves, having Gods Law that was once written in Tables of ſtone, firmely, and plainly written in the fleſhly tables of your heartes. Be like <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throes</hi> Iudges, men of trueth, receiving no falſe nor ſuſpected witneſſes, pronouncing no unjuſt nor partiall ſentences. Be like <hi>Iethroes</hi> Iudges, hating covetouſneſſe, as the ſtaine of your Courtes, the baine of your conſciences, the ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer and ſtifler of Iuſtice, the death and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſoules: that when you ſhall put off your ſcarlet robes, you may put on the long white robe of Saints, and when you ſhall be removed from theſe ſeates of juſtice, you may be admitted into a ſeate of glory: and may follow the bleſſed Lambe whereſoever he goes.</p>
            <p>Grave and learned Counſellors, you muſt be like <hi>Iethroes</hi> Iudges, men of courage to pleade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt prophaneſſe, men fearing God, as pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and examples of holineſſe: men of truth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173660:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ſetting a good countenance upon a bad cauſe: men hating covetouſnes, leſt it be truly wrote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your graves, as it was upon the Tombſtone of <hi>Trinullius, Hîc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andem quieſcit mortuus qui vivus requievit nunquam:</hi> Here he reſtes in mould, who whilſt he lived, could never reſt for gold, nor ſuffered them to reſt that would. Think godlineſſe your greateſt gaine: Pleade for Chriſt, and hee will pleade for you, that when you ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from theſe barres, to anſwer for your owne ſinnes at the barre and tribunall of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate, you may finde mercy and favour with God, and you alſo may follow the bleſſed Lamb whereſoever he will.</p>
            <p>Iurers and witneſſes, you alſo muſt be like <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throes</hi> Iudges, men of courage, whom greatneſſe of perſon cannot daunt; men fearing God, whom no private affection can command; men of truth, whom no perjuries can attaint; men that hate covetouſneſſe, and ſay with <hi>Balaam,</hi> if <hi>Balaac</hi> would give me his houſefull of golde and ſilver, I will not be ſuborned or hired to deflect one haires breadth from the Eclipticke line of truth: that when you have decided controverſies among your brethren, God may have no controverſie with you; when you have witneſſed what poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions belong to men, you may have a witneſſe in your owne conſciences, that your ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God, and you alſo may follow the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lambe whereſoever he goes.</p>
            <p>And let all of us be like <hi>Iethroes</hi> Iudges, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on courage to fight the Lords battells, armed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173660:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> with his feare, girded with his truth as with a gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, hating the ruſt and canker of the unrighteous Mammon, that when God ſhall finiſh our evill dayes of ſinne, hee may be pleaſed to quiet our clamorous conſciences, to pardon our ſinnes, to ſave our ſoules, and to receive both our bodies and ſoules into his bleſſed kingdome, and all of us may follow the bleſſed Lambe whereſoever he goeth. That we may be filled with the glory of the Father, be made partakers of an infinite happineſſe purchaſed by the Sonne, be raviſht with the ineffable comfort of the holy Ghoſt: to which holy, bleſſed, glorious and immortall Trinity be rendred and aſcribed of us, and all Gods Saints throughout the world, all power, praiſe, glory, thanks and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, from this time forth, and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:173660:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
